Finding Aid for Marion T. Marzolf papers, ca. 1961-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marion T. Marzolf papers circa 1961-1995, 1980-1995
Marzolf, Marion T.
4 linear feet
9623 Aa 2
Journalist, professor in the University of Michigan Department of Communication. The series in the collection include Personal/Research, Teaching, and Departmental. Personal/Research relates to awards received, research interests and her involvement in Women in Communication, Inc. The Teaching series includes course materials for classes in journalism, later communication, and the American Culture Program. The Departmental series concerns her activities within the department of communication, including its various reorganizations.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Marion T. Marzolf (donor no. 5004 ) in April 1995.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marion Tuttle Marzolf has committed her life to the education of journalists. In a teaching career that spanned over thirty years, she taught in the Department of Journalism and Communication, the Scandinavian Studies Program and the American Culture Program of the University of Michigan.
Marzolf earned a B.A. in Journalism at Michigan State University in 1952. She worked as a reporter, a copywriter, and a free-lance writer for The Washington Post, the Biloxi Bulletin, and the South Kent News. In 1963 Marzolf earned an M.A. in Journalism from the University of Michigan. She subsequently earned a Ph.D. in American Culture from the same university in 1972.
Although she began as a journalist, Marzolf's career focused on teaching and administration. Her concern with educating journalists at the undergraduate and graduate levels led her to develop new courses, write grants, and spearhead a minority workshop for high school students. Marzolf's work to educate journalists spread beyond the Ann Arbor campus into the national arena. She served on numerous committees in both the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) and Women in Communications, Inc. (WIC).
In addition to teaching, Marzolf held a variety of administrative posts throughout the university. In the Department of Communication, she served as director of Undergraduate Studies, director of the M.A. Program in Journalism and in Mass Communication, and finally as Associate Chair. During her administrative career the Department of Communication faced reorganization of its programs and structure. Both her administrative work and her work on committees within the department reflect her role in this process. Her broader interests are reflected in her other administrative posts as director of the Scandinavian Studies Program within the Department of Germanic Languages and Literature and as acting director of the American Culture Program.
One of Marzolf's interests was the High School Minority Summer Workshop, which alternated between Wayne State, the University of Michigan and Michigan State. This program supported high school students interested in pursuing journalism careers through an intense summer program.
A distinguished publication record emphasizes Marzolf's various research interests. Two books Civilizing Voices: American Press Criticism 1880-1950 (1990) and The Danish-Language Press in America (1972) concentrate on Marzolf's interest in print and ethnic press. A third book, Up from the Footnote: A History of Women Journalists (1977), was awarded second prize for best book in Journalism History by Kappa Tau Alpha in 1978. Marzolf has also presented papers at numerous conferences throughout the country.
Marion T. Marzolf was well respected by her peers inside and outside of the University of Michigan community. In August 1994 she was awarded the William Taft Kappa Tau Alpha Outstanding Adviser award at AJEMC, and in 1990, she was honored with the Faculty Recognition Award at the University of Michigan.
The Marion T. Marzolf papers document not only her career in the journalism and communication at the University of Michigan, but also the curricular changes that occurred during her career. The collection has been divided into three series: Personal/Research, Teaching, and Departmental.
Subjects:
Marzolf, Marion.; Journalism--Study and teaching--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Communication.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women in Communications, Inc.; Women journalists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Journalists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Personal/Research 1971-1993
  Personal/Research (0.7 linear ft.; 1971-1993) documents Marzolf's personal research and interests. Three subseries, Awards, Research, and Women In Communication, Inc. (WICI) are arranged alphabetically by topic. Her research on the Michigan Ethnic Press includes surveys conducted for her book and provides a wealth of information about the ethnic press and its development throughout the state. Divided by ethnic group, these surveys provide the dates and places of publication for newspapers throughout the state. Numerous conference papers and unpublished works are also included in this series. Records and reports from the student chapter of Women in Communication, Inc., for which Marzolf served as an advisor, document not only her years as advisor but also the activities of the organization.
  - Awards 1977-1990 (Box 1)
  - Research 1971-1990
    - Conference Papers 1971-1988 (Box 1)
    - Kerner plus 10, 1977 (Box 1)
    - LSA and SROP Applications 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Ethnic Press Survey (Surveys arranged by ethnic group) (Box 1)
    - New Directions in Television Studies Conference (Proceedings) 1983 (Box 1)
    - Unpublished Papers 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Women in Communication, Inc. (WICI) 1953-1993
    - UN Decade for Women Conference 1980 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Student Chapter 1953-1993
      - Bylaws 1953-1982 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence. 1982-1993 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - Reports 1981-1982 (Box 1)
- Teaching 1961-1994
  Teaching (1.00 linear ft.; 1961-1995) consists of Marzolf's course materials from classes taught in journalism, communication and in both the American Culture and the Scandinavian Studies Programs. Materials from American Culture, Communications, and Journalism are arranged by course number. Her teaching syllabi from thirty plus years in journalism and communication comprise the bulk of this series; however, some courses have complete sets of notes and teaching materials. One of the first courses she taught at the University of Michigan, probably as a teaching assistant, is documented as well as the course in Basic Newswriting, which she supervised. Information Gathering for Mass Media (Com. 250/Jrn. 500), a course funded by a grant, is also completely documented.
  - American Culture Program 1973-1981
    - Report 1976 (Box 1)
    - Syllabi and Bibliographies 1973-1981 (Box 1)
  - Communications 1971-1994
    - Media and Mass Communication (103) 1978-1982 (Box 1)
    - Information Gathering for the Mass Media (250) 1984-1993
      - Assignments 1988-1990 (Box 1)
      - Course Introduction/Syllabus 1987-1993 (Box 1)
      - Final Projects 1988 (Box 1)
      - Grant 1984-1988 (Box 1)
      - License Agreement 1985 (Box 1)
      - Notes 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - Planning 1987-1990 (Box 1)
      - Winter 1993 Plans, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Basic Newswriting (290) 1980-1989
      - Syllabi 1989 (Box 1)
      - TA handbook 1980 (Box 1)
    - Writing for Mass Media (302) 1973-1990 (Box 2)
    - Analyzing Print Journalism (330) 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - The Media in American History (400) 1980-1984 (Box 2)
    - Analyzing the Media (403) 1983-1986 (Box 2)
    - Women in Journalism (500/501) 1971-1990 (Box 2)
    - Information Gathering for Mass Media (500) 1985 (Box 2)
    - Journalistic Ethics and Criticism (545) 1986-1992 (Box 2)
  - Journalism circa 1961-1991
    - Social role of the Mass Media (201) 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Basic News Writing (290) 1975 (Box 2)
    - Writing for Mass Audiences (301/302) 1967-1977 (Box 2)
    - The Media in American History (400) 1970-1979 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Journalist (409) 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - Journalism 410 circa 1961 (Box 2)
    - Media and City (500) 1991 (Box 2)
    - Society and Mass Media (552) 1971 (Box 2)
    - The Ethnic Press (558) 1978 (Box 2)
- Departmental 1970-1995
  Departmental (2.0 linear ft.; 1970-1995) files indicate the changes in curriculum and the changes in the departmental structure during the 1980s and early 1990s. The files are arranged alphabetically within each department. Files for the Minority Summer Workshop are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  Since Marzolf was involved in administration, her files include materials on committees, programs and proposals from the department. Long-range planning is a major focus of the files from the mid-1980s to the mid-1990s. These document the writing of a mission statement for the department and the struggles to reorganize the department. Information on awards and honors given by the department are also included. The history of the Mary Lou Butcher Award is particularly well documented.
  - Department of Communication 1972-1995
    - Alumni 1990 (Box 3)
    - ASNE Conference 1987-1991 (Box 3)
    - Chair 1989-1993 (Box 3)
    - Committee to review M.A. Programs, Minutes 1992 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Handbook 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Mass Communication
      - 1972-1982 (Box 3)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - 1992 (Box 3)
    - M.A. Workshop (Box 3)
    - Proposed Courses 1985 (Box 3)
    - T.A. Appointments 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Undergraduate Program (Box 3)
  - Department of Journalism and Communication 1970-1994
    - Accreditation 1975-1991 (Box 3)
    - Awards and Honors
      - Brumm and Campbell Award 1970-1988 (Box 3)
      - Mary Lou Butcher Award 1976-1992 (Box 3)
      - Honors Program 1982-1988 (Box 3)
      - Leland Stone Award 1973-1991 (Box 3)
    - Defining Journalism 1994 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Handbook 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Search Committee 1987-1993 (Box 3)
    - History of the Department 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Internships 1976-1988 (Box 3)
    - Long Range Plan
      - Bylaws 1992-1993 (Box 3)
      - Five Year Plan 1985-1993 (Box 3)
      - Journalism at Michigan (Report), 1994 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Mission 1990-1994 (Box 3)
      - Tenure Policy 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Merger, Correspondence 1994 (Box 4)
    - Minutes
      - Faculty Meetings 1990-1995 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1971-1994 (Box 4)
    - Philosophy 1972 (Box 4)
    - Policies Manual 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - Professional in Residence 1992 (Box 4)
    - Requirements 1992 (Box 4)
    - Review of M.A. (Box 4)
    - Revisions in Program (Box 4)
    - Weber Fund (Box 4)
  - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of
    - Committees 1990-1995 (Box 4)
    - Report of the Faculty Advising Committee on the Department of Communication 1995 (Box 4)
    - SACUA 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Minority Summer Workshop 1988-1992
    The Minority Summer Workshop was a joint effort between the University of Michigan, Michigan State University and Wayne State University. Marzolf was instrumental in seeking funding and support within the university and from grant agencies, particularly the Dow Jones Fund. Correspondence between units, schools and grant agencies reveal the successes as well as the problems of the program. Schedules, reports and proposals provide a picture of the workshop as a whole.
    - Correspondence
      - 1988 (Box 4)
      - 1989 (Box 4)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - Evaluations 1989 (Box 4)
    - Final Report (Box 4)
    - Katherine Green 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Michigan State 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - Minority Affairs Committee 1988 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1988-1992 (Box 4)
    - Office of Minority Affairs 1988-1992 (Box 4)
    - Participant 1989 (Box 4)
    - Planning and Schedules 1989 (Box 4)
    - Proposals 1989-1993 (Box 4)
    - Publicity 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - Reunion 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - Teacher's Workshop 1988-1989 (Box 4)